Guide to Alice N. Susag papers 1917-1984
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Alice N. Susag papers,
1917-1984
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-2681 MHSlibrary@mt.gov
MC 348
Susag, Alice Narveson,1889-1987.
1.5 linear foot of shelf space
This collection consists of the diaries (1917-1918, 1928-1984) of Alice N. Susag, who homesteaded with her husband Oswald E. Susag, south of Scobey, Montana.
Biographical Note
Alice Melvina Narveson was born in Alstad, Wisconsin, on December 8, 1889, the first child of Knute and Julia (Holt) Narveson. About 1907 Alice began working for her uncle T. J. Anderson's boarding house in Belgrade, Minnesota. After studying secretarial skills at night school she was promoted to bookkeeper for her uncle's department store. Alice met Oswald Edwin Susag, a fellow employee, and they were married October 18, 1911.
In 1916, Oswald Susag homesteaded 160 acres of land 16 miles south of Scobey, Montana. Alice, the couple's two small children, and Alice's sister and brother moved to the homestead in 1917. During World War I, Alice and her neighbors organized a Ladies Aid Society to sew bandages for the Army.
Oswald and Alice Susag raised wheat and oats of their dryland farm and also ran the Kahle post office. The Susags were able to maintain their farm through the drought and depression by supplementing their income by selling butter and eggs in Scobey. The Susags retired from active farming in the late 1950s and their son Ralph took over management of the farm.
Oswald Susag died on January 28, 1971. Alice continued to live on the farm until moving to Scobey in 1979. She died in Scobey February 5, 1987, at the age of 97. [based on biographical sketch by daughter Pearl Susag Craft and son Ralph Waldo Susag.]
Collection consists of Alice Susag's diaries, 1917-1918 and 1928-1984. The diaries document her travel to Montana, her first year on the homestead, everyday activities on the dryland farm, running the Kahle post office, her butter and egg business, her social activities, and her family life.
Arranged by series
Collection is open for research
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Farmers--Montana--Daniels County.
Homesteaders--Montana--Daniels County.
Daniels County (Mont.)--Biography.
Montana
Agriculture
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Biographical Materials
  - "Alice Melvina Narveson Susag, her life as written by her daughter, Pearl Susag Craft, and son, Ralph Waldo Susag", 1901 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
- Diaries
  - Diary, April 1917-April 1918 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Diaries, 1928-1945 (Box-folder 1 / 3-7)
  - Diaries, 1945-1961 (Box-folder 2 / 1-9)
  - Diaries, 1962-1977 (Box-folder 3 / 1-8)
  - Diaries, 1978-1984 (Box-folder 4 / 1-4)
- Miscellaneous
  - Market prices during depression, poems, cards, list of widows in Scobey, etc. (removed from diaries), 1932-1982 (Box-folder 4 / 5)
- Clippings
  - Predominantly re health and farm matters (removed from diaries), 1963-1980 (Box-folder 4 / 6)